<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>https://jnrowe.github.io/</id>
  <title>JNRowe - Posts tagged politics</title>
  <updated>2021-03-24T17:32:32.888021+00:00</updated>
  <link href="https://jnrowe.github.io/"/>
  <link href="https://jnrowe.github.io/blog/tag/politics/atom.xml"/>
  <generator uri="https://ablog.readthedocs.org/" version="0.10.14">ABlog</generator>
  <subtitle>Ramblings of a tired mind</subtitle>
  <entry>
    <id>https://jnrowe.github.io/thoughts/metro_city.html</id>
    <title>Burning down the streets</title>
    <updated>2017-09-03T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>James Rowe</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="section" id="burning-down-the-streets"&gt;

&lt;blockquote class="epigraph"&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;The whole thing makes me wonder whether a modern reintroduction of the
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charivari"&gt;skimmington ride&lt;/a&gt; for social media is long overdue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="attribution"&gt;—Stephen Roberts, eloquent friend&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few months ago a work colleague asked if I could help his wife with an art
project she was working on.  The premise was simple and rather enticing, so
I jumped at the chance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The basic idea was to mine Twitter for its copious poison and visualise any
patterns that emerge.  We quickly hit upon the idea that some poison was so
obvious that &lt;em&gt;even&lt;/em&gt; the Twitter folks would acknowledge and reject it, and
piggybacking off of that would trim down the work considerably.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="mining-the-abyss"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Mining the abyss&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My task was simple: ingest a massive lump of &lt;abbr title="JavaScript Object Notation"&gt;JSON&lt;/abbr&gt;, process it &lt;em&gt;somehow&lt;/em&gt; and spit out results that could be used in an
artsy manner that I would likely not understand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The initial concept worked by scanning a firehose of tweets for keywords which
seemed likely to be hugely poisonous, and then create a &lt;abbr title="Directed Acyclic Graph"&gt;DAG&lt;/abbr&gt; as the basis to
rate users who were retweeting them.  Later versions were self-training using
a naïve Bayes classifier, which allowed us to find offensive tweets using words
I was previously happily unaware of.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Early on it became obvious that another effect presented itself.  There were
&lt;em&gt;masses&lt;/em&gt; of users who were retweeting users who would later be banned, and
those retweeting users would move on to retweeting new users who themselves
would often end up banned.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="Route of evil" class="align-right" src="../../_images/final_plight.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The interesting point to me was that there were large numbers of &lt;em&gt;actual&lt;/em&gt; users
— not bots — who redirect the hate storm and almost nothing else.  Many of
these users were in an anechoic chamber, sucking in tweets from many users and
spitting them back out to virtually no one.  I thought it would be interesting
to work only on the final nodes; weighted by those users who receive close to
no retweets and low user interaction but with histories of retweeting large
numbers of banned and suspended users.  I called it RageRank, because I’m aware
of &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pagerank"&gt;Page Rank&lt;/a&gt; and lack an imagination.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The arty part of the project became known informally as Final Spite, after an
early visualisation effort with animated clone after clone walking along
a &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Final_Fight"&gt;Final Fight&lt;/a&gt; background spewing a tweet bubble as their energy bar
depleted.  Each new visualisation started from a map, much like the game’s
levels, and showed a real city with its real occupants.  The intent was to
allow people to experience a location they knew but with its foetid underbelly
exposed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Final_Fight"&gt;&lt;img alt="Final Fight One on the GBA" class="align-right" src="../../_images/final_fight_one.png" style="width: 237.60000000000002px; height: 158.4px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="what-happened-next"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What happened next?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What happened next saddened and surprised me in equal quantities; visitors to
the site doxxed a heap of the displayed retweeters almost immediately.  So much
in fact that the site was taken down within a day, and the work became a mostly
offline exhibit in a little gallery for other evening school art students.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can understand the sentiment in many ways, and perhaps should have seen it
coming.  When I saw a person I knew in a visualisation I was ashamed, truly
ashamed.  I mean not to the point of thinking it is appropriate to post all
their personal details for the internet vigilantes, but enough that I knew
I would not want to be linked to them through work or social circles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, the end result was really neat even on the smaller canvas it has to
live on.  Seeing that level of vitriolic rage is not fun, but realising that
much of it is vented in to nowhere does soften it a little.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="sidebar"&gt;
&lt;p class="sidebar-title"&gt;Alternative mappings&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having seen the tweets of someone I know pop up, and digging around a little
to see how hateful those tweets were it became clear there was an equally
toxic topic that could be mapped in a similar manner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Following the game theme, perhaps a &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prince_of_Persia:_The_Sands_of_Time"&gt;Prince of Persia: The Sands of Time&lt;/a&gt;
affair that shows the changing hopes, dreams and promises of the anechoic
brexit promoters from early 2016 up to today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="fall-out"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Fall out&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the things that surprised me most was that initially I had primed the
data by looking at users who followed users that have been suspended or banned.
After digging in to a few examples to verify the method’s efficacy I noticed
that there are bidirectional follows to the final nodes where one user appears
to be the polar opposite of the other, almost in an &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alf_Garnett"&gt;Alf Garnett&lt;/a&gt; versus
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peppa_Pig"&gt;Peppa Pig&lt;/a&gt; scale.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It took me a while to think of a possible cause — beyond a simple modelling
error — that could explain this.  Sadly after recognising a top five rage
retweeter in a local town it became somewhat obvious, there are occasionally
business and familial ties involved.  There are seemingly swathes of the
populace who choose to accept public association with the caustic members of
society, even when there is a simple unfollow button you can hit to distance
yourself from them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let us be frank and honest for a moment.  You’re giving the appearance of tacit
approval to people’s views when you continue to follow them, even if you’re not
actively engaging with them.  The simple act of not confronting them is
normalising the behaviour.  If you’re not calling them out on it, you’re doing
yourself and society at large a serious injustice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
    <link href="https://jnrowe.github.io/thoughts/metro_city.html" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>The whole thing makes me wonder whether a modern reintroduction of the
 skimmington ride  for social media is long overdue.</summary>
    <category term="politics" label="politics"/>
    <category term="noise" label="noise"/>
    <published>2017-09-03T00:00:00+01:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://jnrowe.github.io/thoughts/brexit_through_the_gift_shop.html</id>
    <title>brexit through the gift shop</title>
    <updated>2018-06-08T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>James Rowe</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="section" id="brexit-through-the-gift-shop"&gt;

&lt;div class="admonition note"&gt;
&lt;p class="admonition-title"&gt;Note&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a public letter to my co-workers, which probably shouldn’t be
public.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="epigraph"&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;If there were in the world today any large number of people who desired
their own happiness more than they desired the unhappiness of others, we
could have a paradise in a few years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="attribution"&gt;—Bertrand Russell&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Monday morning, a friend and co-worker stood up and rage quit.  And I really
do mean rage quit, it even included a short stand up quarrel in the car park.
Obviously, nobody has spoke about &lt;em&gt;anything&lt;/em&gt; else since…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="background"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We used to work in an environment where we could &lt;span class="xref std std-doc"&gt;reject projects&lt;/span&gt; on moral grounds with ease.  In fact, &lt;abbr title="Institutional Review Board"&gt;IRBs&lt;/abbr&gt; exist for that exact reason.  Times were good,
projects were plentiful, and it was just the way things were.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is definitely no longer true.  As we continue to rearrange some projects
for their move to the continent, and lose access to many of the future projects
we have prepared for, there has been a significant push back on personal project
choice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To some extent it should be expected.  We’ve lost fifteen percent of our
&lt;abbr title="Research and Development"&gt;R&amp;amp;D&lt;/abbr&gt; workforce to the European offices
already, in many ways those of us that remain(for example: &lt;em&gt;me&lt;/em&gt;) are the less
valued employees.  Yes, this is harsh, but it also the reality.  Just because
you don’t like it, doesn’t change the reality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, there are quite a few people further down the ladder who can no longer rely
on the more valued workers to object-in-unity to immoral works.  And there are
a fair few who have only just discovered they were never holding the chips, and
being let go is a real possibility(we’re &lt;em&gt;way&lt;/em&gt; beyond the pool of voluntary
redundancies at this point).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="collective-bargaining"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Collective bargaining&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, object-in-unity is pretty much dead.  And it has really surprised me quite
how fractious some of the arguments now are.  Given that people are basically
fighting for scraps the gloves have well and truly come off, which I suppose
should be expected.  However, I thought — or at least hoped — we were better
than this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With some people, quite rightly, being concerned for their own careers there has
been some real vitriol aimed at the exitter.  I understand their argument; his
rage quit &lt;em&gt;will&lt;/em&gt; mean that project is dead&lt;a class="footnote-reference brackets" href="#s1" id="id1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;, and with it the work of the
peripheral workers has gone too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It isn’t helped by the fact that it turns out this particular worker is — we’ve
just found out — independently wealthy through the sale of a &lt;span class="xref std std-doc"&gt;side project&lt;/span&gt; about five years ago.  Seemingly, a minority of people believe
it would be okay if someone’s morals put them in the poor house, but less
so if they have a cushion to soften the blow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="whats-coming-next"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Whats coming next?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="epigraph"&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lisa is a sellout! Lisa is a sellout! Lisa, what’s a sellout?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="attribution"&gt;—Ralph Wiggum&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clearly this is going to continue for the foreseeable future.  There are a few
of us who, to put it frankly, are basically on gardening leave while this mess
is being sorted out.  The outcome is either you’ll find yourself doing different
work in a years time, or you’ll be made redundant.  It could be much, &lt;em&gt;much&lt;/em&gt;
worse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I, for one, haven’t had a tier-one project since August 2016, haven’t published
a notable work since October 2017, and have only been cited once this year.  If
anybody understands the feeling that your career is dead, then surely it is me.
However, now is not the time to be turning on your co-workers(and in many cases
close friends).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My career is over in its current form, my future is close to non-existent at
this point, and I mourn what now feels like a wasted fifteen years of my life.
Not one of those things would be less true if somebody was now grinding on
projects that they believed to be reprehensible.  In fact, they’d remain true
and I’d feel far worse for having to live with the damage I’m doing to that
person.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please, I beg of you, consider the outcome we’ve seen in some other cases over
the past few months.  Nobody you deal with is happy with this, we’re just doing
what can to get through it as best we know how.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="rubric"&gt;Footnotes&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;dl class="footnote brackets"&gt;
&lt;dt class="label" id="s1"&gt;&lt;span class="brackets"&gt;&lt;a class="fn-backref" href="#id1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;&lt;p&gt;Yes, that is a terrible bus-factor problem.  The powers that be
&lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; have seen it coming, but probably missed the point where the
other people with the necessary skills have been moved to Germany.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
    <link href="https://jnrowe.github.io/thoughts/brexit_through_the_gift_shop.html" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>This is a public letter to my co-workers, which probably shouldn’t be
public.</summary>
    <category term="work" label="work"/>
    <category term="politics" label="politics"/>
    <published>2018-06-08T00:00:00+01:00</published>
  </entry>
</feed>
