<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>https://jnrowe.github.io/</id>
  <title>JNRowe - Posts tagged site</title>
  <updated>2022-03-11T11:45:58.162146+00:00</updated>
  <link href="https://jnrowe.github.io/"/>
  <link href="https://jnrowe.github.io/blog/tag/site/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <generator uri="https://ablog.readthedocs.org/" version="0.10.23">ABlog</generator>
  <subtitle>Ramblings of a tired mind</subtitle>
  <entry>
    <id>https://jnrowe.github.io/thoughts/the_returned.html</id>
    <title>Return to rambling</title>
    <updated>2014-01-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>James Rowe</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;section id="return-to-rambling"&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I kept a public journal from about 2003 until 2009, with a new entry about every
three days.  I enjoyed the act of writing it greatly, and often looked forward
to the period of contemplation it would create.  However, eventually I found
I had to kill it, but not because of waning enthusiasm as is so often the case.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had simply become incredibly frustrated and entirely fed up with having to
censor myself; “unprofessional” thoughts, fear of discussing hot political
issues, &amp;amp;c.  I realised, towards the end, that I would spend about the same
amount of time editing a post as I would writing it.  Sometimes I would spend an
hour on a short post and finally delete it entirely.  &lt;em&gt;All&lt;/em&gt; the love was gone,
&lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section id="unleash-the-shout-hole"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Unleash the shout-hole&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So why return?  Simple, I’ve reached a stage in my life where I don’t have to be
quite so concerned with outbound appearances for the sake of professional life,
and I should feel free to express myself how I wish in my personal life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don’t get me wrong, I’m not about to start writing about whatever noisy issue
I can find just because I can.  I’m not, nor have I ever wished to be, a tabloid
journalist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this resurrection and the previous incarnations has always been
as an outlet for some of my views.  It is a side-effect should it be read by
others.  However, some of my fondest memories of writing have been the
conversations that have arisen from folks who’ve contacted me about an entry.
I’ve engaged with some extremely interesting people this way, some of whom
I remain in touch with to this day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I &lt;em&gt;always&lt;/em&gt; have an open invitation to thank me, correct me, shame me or berate
me for the opinions I express or information I spread.  And that invitation is
absolutely extended to this site and the new content I post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="https://jnrowe.github.io/thoughts/the_returned.html" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>I kept a public journal from about 2003 until 2009, with a new entry about every
three days.  I enjoyed the act of writing it greatly, and often looked forward
to the period of contemplation it would create.  However, eventually I found
I had to kill it, but not because of waning enthusiasm as is so often the case.</summary>
    <category term="blog" label="blog"/>
    <category term="site" label="site"/>
    <published>2014-01-27T00:00:00+00:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://jnrowe.github.io/thoughts/comments.html</id>
    <title>Ugh, why no comments???</title>
    <updated>2018-01-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>James Rowe</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;section id="ugh-why-no-comments"&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many moons ago, when my blog was hosted elsewhere I built a comment system for
it.  Comments came in, I learnt things, I was corrected when wrong.  Times were
good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, my own personal version of &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eternal_September"&gt;eternal september&lt;/a&gt; occurred at some point
and the comments became almost valueless(spam or unrelated rants).  I disabled
them; times were good again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then back in 2009, I re-added comments via Disqus.  There was almost no spam,
and the comments felt mostly useful.  Disqus remained for a little while, but
I never felt comfortable with it.  It forces an &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://donw.io/post/github-comments/"&gt;enormous amount of tracking&lt;/a&gt;
on visitors, and does so regardless of whether an actual comment is being
posted.  I disabled it; times were good again again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section id="but-i-want-to-comment"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;But, I want to comment!!!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cool, I like comments.  I’ve learned a lot of things via comments about this
site and its previous incarnations.  I absolutely welcome them, but I don’t
want to wade through spam or enable enormous amounts of tracking on visitors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to comment then drop me a &lt;a class="reference external" href="mailto:jnrowe&amp;#37;&amp;#52;&amp;#48;gmail&amp;#46;com"&gt;mail&lt;/a&gt;, reply via &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://indieweb.org/POSSE"&gt;your own site&lt;/a&gt; or as
a last resort &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/JNRowe/jnrowe.github.io/issues"&gt;open an issue&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If your comment is more of a clarification or a fix, you may even want to
consider a pull request.  If my friend Matt can &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/JNRowe/jnrowe.github.io/commit/64539db44dbd7ec562bc83bdf7a672a78c71e939"&gt;do it&lt;/a&gt;, so can you!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="https://jnrowe.github.io/thoughts/comments.html" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>Many moons ago, when my blog was hosted elsewhere I built a comment system for
it.  Comments came in, I learnt things, I was corrected when wrong.  Times were
good.</summary>
    <category term="site" label="site"/>
    <published>2018-01-24T00:00:00+00:00</published>
  </entry>
</feed>
