<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>https://jnrowe.github.io/</id>
  <title>JNRowe - Posts tagged hobbies</title>
  <updated>2022-03-11T11:45:56.502222+00:00</updated>
  <link href="https://jnrowe.github.io/"/>
  <link href="https://jnrowe.github.io/blog/tag/hobbies/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <generator uri="https://ablog.readthedocs.org/" version="0.10.23">ABlog</generator>
  <subtitle>Ramblings of a tired mind</subtitle>
  <entry>
    <id>https://jnrowe.github.io/thoughts/side_projects.html</id>
    <title>Side-projects</title>
    <updated>2013-12-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>James Rowe</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;section id="side-projects"&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chatting with my brother yesterday he expressed some disbelief when I mentioned
&lt;em&gt;yet another&lt;/em&gt; friend who has a website related to some topic we were discussing:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Does everyone you know run a website?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes, yes, they do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It hadn’t really occurred to me until I was reading a write up of a co-workers
weekend hack.  The majority of nerdy people I know run websites, create
iPhone/android apps or have other side projects in various states of completion.
It’s just How Things Work®&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I guess it is mostly a cultural issue, one which is quite strong behind the
engineering side of the curtain in my workplace.  Sure, there are some “5:01”
types who are out of the door as soon as the bell rings, but there are an awful
lot who extend their tech creations in to a downtime hobby or side business.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To relate this to my brother I think of a family party we attended this past
weekend.  When people asked me what my brother does I’d say that he works in
logistics, and the conversation drifts from there.  When talking to the
extended family that often seemed to head toward being about material
possessions that work may afford him.  However, I’ve noticed in the past when
I’m talking to people I’d call friends it often quickly digresses in to strange
discussions about box packing, routing, &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Travelling_salesman_problem"&gt;the curse of travelling salesmen&lt;/a&gt; or
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bridges_of_Konigsberg"&gt;bridges in some foreign land&lt;/a&gt;.  Because of the math and technology
implications many of my friends have written tools to explore some of the
practical and theoretical issues faced in logistics… often for fun.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section id="it-is-all-about-me"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;It is all about me&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m not working on any public facing websites right now&lt;a class="footnote-reference brackets" href="#s1" id="id1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;, but I do play
with a few public facing projects from time to time that should head towards
proving my point.  I’m picking a few semi-randomly to illustrate a little
diversity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="admonition note"&gt;
&lt;p class="admonition-title"&gt;Note&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To save myself some researching effort I’ll only link to things from &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/JNRowe/"&gt;my
GitHub profile&lt;/a&gt; or links from my browser’s bookmarks, but that should be
descriptive enough to get the point across.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;section id="gentoo-packages"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Gentoo packages&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the past decade I’ve spent a lot of time hacking on things related to
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://gentoo.org/"&gt;Gentoo&lt;/a&gt;.  Some of that for work projects and some of it for &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://jnrowe-misc.readthedocs.io/"&gt;personal
projects&lt;/a&gt;.  I’ve also experienced my fair share of troubles, and have &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?email1=jnrowe%40gmail.com&amp;amp;emailassigned_to1=1&amp;amp;emailcc1=1&amp;amp;emaillongdesc1=1&amp;amp;emailreporter1=1&amp;amp;emailtype1=substring&amp;amp;query_format=advanced"&gt;reported
a few bugs&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At one time I even hoped to &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://bugs.gentoo.org/show_bug.cgi?id=142090"&gt;become a developer&lt;/a&gt;, but that didn’t work out for
a bunch of reasons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="github2"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;github2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a year I &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/ask/python-github2/graphs/contributors"&gt;maintained&lt;/a&gt; a relatively popular &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/ask/python-github2"&gt;API wrapper&lt;/a&gt; to GitHub.  I did
this because I found it fun.  It provided no economic benefit to me, and I never
expected it to.  I know a lot of people used it when building their own toy
projects and websites, because many were kind enough to link to it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="pyisbn"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;pyisbn&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For seven years I’ve maintained a small library for &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/JNRowe/pyisbn/"&gt;validating ISBNs&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;em&gt;Yes, that is absolutely as boring as it sounds&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was never meant to be used by others, I just needed something to validate
entries in my e-book database.  Other people started using it, many for their
own weird side projects including a number of book retail websites.  It has
amassed literally tens of thousands of downloads from &lt;abbr title="Python Package Index"&gt;PyPI&lt;/abbr&gt;, but you really
shouldn’t trust the dubious statistics from &lt;abbr title="Python Package Index"&gt;PyPI&lt;/abbr&gt; ;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="rdial"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;rdial&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;rdial&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; is a &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://rdial.readthedocs.io/"&gt;time tracking tool&lt;/a&gt;, and a perfect example for me.  I played
with it for over a year before anyone else saw it, just because it scratched an
itch I had.  I never imagined it would be useful to others.  Turns out it was,
and there is now a small yet faithful band of users.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I even received the great honour of a few summer evening beers for releasing it.
A beer being second only to a patch in the table of project endorsements
that I subscribe to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="upoints-nee-earth-distance"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;upoints&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; née &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;earth_distance&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://jnrowe.github.io/upoints/"&gt;upoints&lt;/a&gt; is a strange one.  It started as a &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://jnrowe.github.io/upoints/geolocation_and_pathcross.html"&gt;stupid hack&lt;/a&gt; to figure out some
silly travel planning drama, it proceeded to take on a life of its own.  Over
the years it attracted a fair amount of users, and I still receive email about
it now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It did have some tangible benefit though, the sadly now defunct website it
eventually spawned opened some nice doors for me.  I didn’t know it would or
could at the time, so it didn’t affect how I spent my time when playing with it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="cut-from-the-pattern"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Cut from the pattern&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This isn’t specific to me, or even to the particularly nerdy among my
co-workers.  If you &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/explore"&gt;dig around on GitHub&lt;/a&gt;, or even &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://makezine.com/"&gt;makezine&lt;/a&gt;, you’ll see
people creating purely because they can.  This isn’t a new phenomenon either.
If you were around pre-GitHub you’d see people making things on Sourceforge.  If
you were around before Sourceforge, you’ll remember the good old days when life
was simpler and people held doors open for you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The point is simple.  Yes, I &lt;em&gt;may&lt;/em&gt; know someone who is working on
project/website related to some topic, but that is only because many of the
people I know are spitting out new projects on what often appears to be a weekly
basis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="rubric"&gt;Footnotes&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;dl class="footnote brackets"&gt;
&lt;dt class="label" id="s1"&gt;&lt;span class="brackets"&gt;&lt;a class="fn-backref" href="#id1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;&lt;p&gt;I really don’t count &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://jnrowe.github.io/"&gt;this site&lt;/a&gt;, as it
is just a jumbled content dump with no real purpose.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="https://jnrowe.github.io/thoughts/side_projects.html" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>Chatting with my brother yesterday he expressed some disbelief when I mentioned
yet another friend who has a website related to some topic we were discussing:</summary>
    <category term="hobbies" label="hobbies"/>
    <category term="projects" label="projects"/>
    <published>2013-12-16T00:00:00+00:00</published>
  </entry>
</feed>
