<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>https://jnrowe.github.io/</id>
  <title>JNRowe - Posts tagged privacy</title>
  <updated>2021-03-24T17:32:32.918241+00:00</updated>
  <link href="https://jnrowe.github.io/"/>
  <link href="https://jnrowe.github.io/blog/tag/privacy/atom.xml"/>
  <generator uri="https://ablog.readthedocs.org/" version="0.10.14">ABlog</generator>
  <subtitle>Ramblings of a tired mind</subtitle>
  <entry>
    <id>https://jnrowe.github.io/thoughts/dopplr_effects.html</id>
    <title>Dopplr defects</title>
    <updated>2014-01-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>James Rowe</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="section" id="dopplr-defects"&gt;

&lt;blockquote class="epigraph"&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Dopplr was a free social networking service, launched in 2007, that allowed
users to create itineraries of their travel plans and spot correlations with
their contacts’ travel plans in order to arrange meetings at any point on
their journey.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="attribution"&gt;—&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dopplr"&gt;dopplr&lt;/a&gt; wikipedia entry&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A couple of months ago &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dopplr"&gt;dopplr&lt;/a&gt; was shut down.  It was perhaps my most
favouritistist of websites, but I didn’t use it.  In fact, I hadn’t visited in
nearly three years and it contained no data I was interested in saving…  but
I still counted it among my favourite sites.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;dopplr had an elegant, yet jaw droppingly beautiful design; a marvel of
simplicity and discoverability.  The functionality was great, who doesn’t like
the idea of discovering happy collisions with old friends?  The implementation
was cool, introducing me to OpenID.  I loved the site enough to read the
&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#backstory"&gt;backstory&lt;/a&gt; when the shutdown news was being passed around, but I still didn’t
want to use it again.  The cost for this functionality was just far too great
for me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I simply couldn’t stomach giving up the information that dopplr required to
function.  It required an enormous amount of vigilance to police your own data
on the way in, to make sure you weren’t sharing things you couldn’t or
shouldn’t.  You could often glean things that people didn’t perhaps realise they
were sharing.  A friend’s weekend to somewhere odd like Bedford wasn’t just
a sign that you could meet up for lunch, it was probably also a sign that they
were visiting Lockheed Martin&lt;a class="footnote-reference brackets" href="#s1" id="id1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;“Oh, Kevin is going to be near me next week!  Hmm, either he is on an
exceptionally long pub crawl or he is about to sign a contract”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I know that dopplr was cool though, it was powerful and it did squeeze a lot
more serendipity out of the world(I forget their actual tagline).  I couldn’t
imagine a better present for 2014 than to find a replacement that I could
actually use, but sadly I can’t even picture how it should work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="rubric"&gt;Footnotes&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;dl class="footnote brackets"&gt;
&lt;dt class="label" id="s1"&gt;&lt;span class="brackets"&gt;&lt;a class="fn-backref" href="#id1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;&lt;p&gt;Your personal examples may vary&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;span class="target" id="backstory"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
    <link href="https://jnrowe.github.io/thoughts/dopplr_effects.html" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>Dopplr was a free social networking service, launched in 2007, that allowed
users to create itineraries of their travel plans and spot correlations with
their contacts’ travel plans in order to arrange meetings at any point on
their journey.</summary>
    <category term="history" label="history"/>
    <category term="privacy" label="privacy"/>
    <published>2014-01-06T00:00:00+00:00</published>
  </entry>
</feed>
