<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>https://jnrowe.github.io/</id>
  <title>JNRowe - Posts tagged probit</title>
  <updated>2021-04-29T22:38:02.800446+00:00</updated>
  <link href="https://jnrowe.github.io/"/>
  <link href="https://jnrowe.github.io/blog/tag/probit/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <generator uri="https://ablog.readthedocs.org/" version="0.10.18">ABlog</generator>
  <subtitle>Ramblings of a tired mind</subtitle>
  <entry>
    <id>https://jnrowe.github.io/articles/probits/index.html</id>
    <title>Project postmortems</title>
    <updated>2014-06-30T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>James Rowe</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;section id="project-postmortems"&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of my favourite things about the day job is the post-project analysis and
postmortems, which we lovingly refer to as &lt;abbr title="Project Obituaries"&gt;probits&lt;/abbr&gt;
internally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section id="background"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I work in heavily structured and standalone project-oriented environment.  In
a decade I can count the number of fluid projects on three fingers.  As I write
this in June 2014 my tier-one project started 21 months ago, and has a delivery
date locked down to a week in 2015.  We’ll deliver on time or a touch early, our
team is known for that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the benefits of working on such strict projects with definite ship dates
and locked schedules is that you always know when a project is complete.  This
also allows us to take advantage of that by inspecting the project as a whole,
spotting the successes and failures within.  Probits are the more informal
dialogue that we pin to the front of each folder.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="what-youll-find"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What you’ll find&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve recently decided I’d like to take a similar approach to some side projects
that I work on, and also try to apply the methods to some more real-life
situations.  This category, and the accompanying index, below are that attempt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="toctree-wrapper compound"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="https://jnrowe.github.io/articles/probits/index.html" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>One of my favourite things about the day job is the post-project analysis and
postmortems, which we lovingly refer to as probits
internally.</summary>
    <category term="probit" label="probit"/>
    <published>2014-06-30T00:00:00+01:00</published>
  </entry>
</feed>
