<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title type="text">JNRowe - Posts tagged life</title>
  <id>https://jnrowe.github.io/blog/tag/life/atom.xml</id>
  <updated>2014-09-03T00:00:00Z</updated>
  <link href="https://jnrowe.github.io/" />
  <link href="https://jnrowe.github.io/blog/tag/life/atom.xml" rel="self" />
  <subtitle type="text">Ramblings of a tired mind</subtitle>
  <generator uri="http://ablog.readthedocs.org" version="0.9.4">ABlog</generator>
  <entry xml:base="https://jnrowe.github.io/blog/tag/life/atom.xml">
    <title type="text">Open Source and enjoyment</title>
    <id>https://jnrowe.github.io/thoughts/burn_out.html</id>
    <updated>2014-09-03T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <published>2014-09-03T00:00:00Z</published>
    <link href="https://jnrowe.github.io/thoughts/burn_out.html" />
    <author>
      <name>James Rowe</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;section&quot; id=&quot;open-source-and-enjoyment&quot;&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few years ago I burned out on Open Source projects, to the point that it was
close to impacting other parts of my life.  I have only myself to blame as
I didn’t manage to distance myself at all well.  Distancing yourself is not easy
to do when your fun hobby for relaxation is the thing that is working against
you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were a variety of incredibly minor issues that piled up Jenga-style.  Then
to carry the weak analogy forward, it toppled over in a split second like Jenga
in a rubber dingy on the rolling seas with a fumbling drunken friend wearing
a blindfold.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve decided to write down a few of the things that were happening, both as an
act of catharsis and to help me spot the problems in future.  Perhaps it will
help others who are experiencing the same thing but haven’t quite spotted the
catalysts yet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;section&quot; id=&quot;dealing-with-needy-users&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Dealing with needy users&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some users seem to feel a disproportionate amount of “you work for me”,
seemingly more so than happens with actual paying customers on other projects
which strikes me as strange.  They’ll bug you endlessly in emails, in the issue
tracker, on &lt;abbr title=&quot;Internet Relay Chat&quot;&gt;IRC&lt;/abbr&gt; and in real life if you end up at the same conference.  You
&lt;em&gt;need&lt;/em&gt; to stop this before it takes hold.  It helps if you can be polite, but
if not just stop it anyway.  It is for &lt;em&gt;your&lt;/em&gt; welfare, so just do it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I actually found myself burning the wrong people towards the peak of that
imaginary Jenga tower.  You need to make a concerted effort to figure out which
people are delivering the seemingly endless grief or perhaps just relentless
&lt;a class=&quot;reference external&quot; href=&quot;http://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/bikeshedding&quot;&gt;bikeshedding&lt;/a&gt;, and stop them.  It is all too easy to accidentally become
annoyed at well meaning useful contributors when you’ve been trawling through
a heap of useless meta-discussion about a change nobody is making.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On one &lt;em&gt;library&lt;/em&gt; project I worked on there was a user who didn’t read the
documentation, couldn’t use the language enough to write tests, yet still
endlessly sucked up support time by opening awful issues and sending pointless
emails wishing to discuss changes they might make.  I kind of hesitate to say
awful issues, but - for example - if you can’t write a two line assertion in
a language you’re not in the target audience for a library in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Those people aren’t even adding value in pointing out deficiencies in
documentation, because they’re not a target user.  It would be like me writing
to &lt;a class=&quot;reference external&quot; href=&quot;http://www.jcb.com/&quot;&gt;JCB&lt;/a&gt; telling them they must document why they use round knobs on the digger
I saw someone else using.  So try spot it early, and put a stop to it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I suspect a big part of the issue here is cost.  I’m sure if there was even
a single penny cost to opening issues or sending a mail it would do wonders for
communication in general.  I suspect that would remain true even if you
reimbursed that penny immediately.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;section&quot; id=&quot;the-simple-answer&quot;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The simple answer&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I figured out how to work with this entirely by accident.  Politely offer
answers that move them away from you.  It is by far the easiest solution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In one instance I suggested alternative packages to an expensive user, with the
hope they’d quietly move on.  Which is evil really, as what you’re really doing
is dreaming that they’ll move on to bother a developer who isn’t you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On another occasion I stole an idea from a friend and said “Sorry, I can’t
figure out how to implement this.  Open a pull request, and I’ll merge it!” to
another.  It worked well, because it stopped the direction-less discussion and
was never going to be followed up with a patch later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;section&quot; id=&quot;dealing-with-unreasonable-requests&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Dealing with unreasonable requests&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I used to get quite annoyed when I received an impolite or unreasonable request
on an Open Source project, nowadays I tend to just respond with pre-canned
answers for most of them.  If you can cut the time it takes to respond to them,
you’ll obviously spend far less time thinking about them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The typical one that springs to mind is a user complaining that you’ve not
licensed your &lt;abbr title=&quot;GNU General Public License&quot;&gt;GPL&lt;/abbr&gt; code in a way which allows them to use it without
contributing anything in return.  I choose reciprocating licences where I can,
because frankly that may be the only value you provide &lt;em&gt;me&lt;/em&gt; as a user.  I get
that some people need to use their Open Source projects as a way to improve
their CV or build a presence, but for many of us it is just for fun and
reciprocation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another example that I recall, but wish I didn’t, was a user &lt;em&gt;telling&lt;/em&gt; me to
recompress a tarball on &lt;abbr title=&quot;Python Package Index&quot;&gt;PyPI&lt;/abbr&gt; because their infrastructure couldn’t support
&lt;strong class=&quot;command&quot;&gt;bzip2&lt;/strong&gt;.  Seems reasonable enough, but it came wrapped in a tirade of
abuse.  I ignored the abuse, uploaded another tarball and then received another
abusive email in return the next day.  That was a long time ago, far before the
burnout started to creep in so I just addressed the actual issue and moved on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;section&quot; id=&quot;the-answer&quot;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The answer&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had forgotten about that whole previous story until at &lt;a class=&quot;reference external&quot; href=&quot;https://europython.eu/&quot;&gt;Europython&lt;/a&gt; a friend
was telling me about someone who was banned from a number of events, hell-banned
on various mailing lists and on forced lockout on Stack Overflow for poisonous
behaviour.  I started to tell my story as an example of strange abusive
behaviour, and it turned out to be the same guy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The point is these people can be everywhere so just don’t let them get to you.
I realise that is both obvious and feels hard to do, but it is quite easy in the
virtual world.  If you have the hell-ban option available just use
it; perhaps there is an ignore option in your issue tracker, add a “send to
trash” rule in your email filter.  Even in person it can be quite easy to do,
just politely acknowledge their issue and move away instead of engaging them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;section&quot; id=&quot;the-solutions&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The solutions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I chose a solution I hate, for all intents and purposes I don’t release new Open
Source projects any longer.  I still work on a lot of projects, and the code is
normally available somewhere for strangers.  However, for the most part I’ve
made a point of not hosting or releasing it in the common places.  This works
for me, but it saddens me deeply.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have a friend who does something interesting to combat the same problems I’ve
mentioned here.  He hooks the issue tracker to only show issues reported by
people in his second-degree &lt;a class=&quot;reference external&quot; href=&quot;http://www.foaf-project.org/&quot;&gt;FOAF&lt;/a&gt; circle or people whose user profile is an
active Open Source contributor.  It works, and it cuts out most of the problem
users, but it is nasty.  I feel it is worse than my “solution” because it still
gives the impression of support to the users you won’t support, but also gives
the impression of bad support through heaps of unanswered issues to the users
who would receive good support.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;The greatest trick the devil ever played was convincing users they had skin
in the game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I may be misappropriating a quote from a great film there, but it is important.
A lot of the actively poisonous people who contact you aren’t providing any real
value to you, and they’re probably never going to.  If you can remove them
somehow you’re probably not losing anything, but you’ll be gaining a whole lot
personally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="https://jnrowe.github.io/blog/tag/life/atom.xml">
    <title type="text">Delayed flashover</title>
    <id>https://jnrowe.github.io/thoughts/delayed_flashover.html</id>
    <updated>2014-04-09T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <published>2014-04-09T00:00:00Z</published>
    <link href="https://jnrowe.github.io/thoughts/delayed_flashover.html" />
    <author>
      <name>James Rowe</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;section&quot; id=&quot;delayed-flashover&quot;&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This weekend a very good friend of mine is taking part in the London Marathon,
and we’re all looking forward to the no-doubt incredible time she’ll finish in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&quot;epigraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;“Fun run” is the excuse losers give &lt;em&gt;before&lt;/em&gt; a race&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Normally, I wouldn’t bother writing anything about such an event but this is
different.  It is different because she is practically a hero to me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m talking about Rach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last summer she gave birth to a bouncing baby girl&lt;a class=&quot;footnote-reference brackets&quot; href=&quot;#s1&quot; id=&quot;id1&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seven months later she is going to complete a marathon.  I would say “planning
to complete”, but I know better at this point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is made all the more impressive because a decade ago we thought we’d lose
her following a serious accident.  As time went on and things improved the
realisation that we’d have a wheelchair-bound-for-life friend kicked in.  And
slowly it became clear that we’d have a crutch-bound-for-life friend.  And
eventually it became quite obvious we’d have a soul-filling running machine to
envy once again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now she has been lucky, very lucky.  But we make our own luck too, and she is an
awesome luck making machine.  To poorly misuse a Pasteur quote that I already
tend to overuse, “luck favours the prepared mind.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If I have one tip for the Dear Reader this week it is this: Keep your
sponsorship options in check, she’ll destroy the target time.  Go Rach!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;admonition note&quot;&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;admonition-title&quot;&gt;Note&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Update&lt;/strong&gt;: Sub-four finish, ‘nuff said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;rubric&quot;&gt;Footnotes&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;dl class=&quot;footnote brackets&quot;&gt;
&lt;dt class=&quot;label&quot; id=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;brackets&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;fn-backref&quot; href=&quot;#id1&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;&lt;p&gt;a term which always make me think I should call child services&lt;a class=&quot;footnote-reference brackets&quot; href=&quot;#s2&quot; id=&quot;id2&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt class=&quot;label&quot; id=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;brackets&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;fn-backref&quot; href=&quot;#id2&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;&lt;p&gt;a term which makes me think they bring fizzy drinks and sugary cakes&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="https://jnrowe.github.io/blog/tag/life/atom.xml">
    <title type="text">Hitting life’s reset button</title>
    <id>https://jnrowe.github.io/thoughts/reset_in_ten.html</id>
    <updated>2014-02-24T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <published>2014-02-24T00:00:00Z</published>
    <link href="https://jnrowe.github.io/thoughts/reset_in_ten.html" />
    <author>
      <name>James Rowe</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;section&quot; id=&quot;hitting-lifes-reset-button&quot;&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Seven months ago while enjoying a little Saturday afternoon cricket picnic,
a friend posed the question:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;“If life had a reset button when would you have used it?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, I understand the point and the purpose of this.  Catherine was hoping to
elicit some deep truths, with the eventual goal that people would bond further.
That doesn’t mean I played the game though.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I recall my answer was somewhat flippant:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;“I’d have used it repeatedly half an hour ago, until I figured out the magic
incantation that convinces that cashier in the ‘Express to join me for
a picnic… and then I would have ditched you suckers.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was an honest-ish answer;  I mean yeah, she may have been worth messing with
the universe for.  It wasn’t, however, the correct kind of reply.  I should
have been describing some dreadful mistake I made, both to make my friends
laugh and also to let them in a little closer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I didn’t choose to answer that way to be deliberately obtuse, I answered
that way simply because it was how I felt at the time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since then, and I direct you to the first three words of this post, I’ve been
mildly obsessed with the question.  I have a twenty heading document where I’ve
described branch points in my life, specifically the ones with the deepest joy
and most painful regrets.  I hoped I’d see a pattern of some kind, and that
would allow me to direct myself toward the happier paths in future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I didn’t, and it hasn’t.  Not even a little bit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don’t seem to find myself in the situations where I could repeat the most
foolish decisions that I really regret.  And I wonder whether that is because
I’ve eventually been smart enough to learn my lessons, or stupid enough that
I’m unable to spot the new mistakes yet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The whole process has been very cathartic though. Despite having
a &lt;em&gt;significantly&lt;/em&gt; higher proportion of regrets than successes in my list,
I kind of enjoying reviewing it in a cringe ridden way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’d really like to thank Catherine for offering the mirror, it has been
intriguing in a terrifying and horrific kind of way.  Unfortunately, I can’t.
It is too late, and there is another lesson for me to learn.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr class=&quot;docutils&quot; /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For what it’s worth, that girl still works at the ‘Express and I’ve done
nothing useful about it.  Internet, this is the foolish truth I proffer you
today.  The others well, they’ll hopefully remain hidden away from view.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="https://jnrowe.github.io/blog/tag/life/atom.xml">
    <title type="text">Murdering morality with ferocious fire</title>
    <id>https://jnrowe.github.io/thoughts/important_balance.html</id>
    <updated>2014-01-25T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <published>2014-01-25T00:00:00Z</published>
    <link href="https://jnrowe.github.io/thoughts/important_balance.html" />
    <author>
      <name>James Rowe</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;section&quot; id=&quot;murdering-morality-with-ferocious-fire&quot;&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;epigraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Morality is herd instinct in the individual.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;attribution&quot;&gt;—Friedrich Nietzsche&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I look back at my life’s work thus far I often find myself asking the
question “was it worth it?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That question isn’t meant in some kind of crazed suicidal manner, I just mean
specifically the projects I’ve worked on and the things I do.  Are they just?
Should I be doing this?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I truly hope it doesn’t come as a surprise to people who know me, but I consider
myself to be a person of strong moral values&lt;a class=&quot;footnote-reference brackets&quot; href=&quot;#s1&quot; id=&quot;id1&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;.  I probably shouldn’t admit
this publicly, but over the years I have turned down several projects I didn’t
feel ethically comfortable working on.  And it has &lt;em&gt;demonstrably&lt;/em&gt; held my career
progression back.  I mostly fine with that.  No, I really am.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The simple fact is that I’m due for a HR review, overdue actually, and these
questions have started to come to the fore again.  I’ll lay in bed thinking
about them, I’ll sit here typing about them, I’ll judge other people to gauge
the validity of my position and I’ll bore people who’ll listen with my
dilemmas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One shouldn’t really use the word “dilemma” here, these issues are practically
the definition of “First World Problems”.  Part of me is disgusted to waste so
much time on frankly trivial introspection, but for better or worse it is
a &lt;em&gt;huge&lt;/em&gt; part of my self-identity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I feel that — to some extent — I’m living a weak, self-imposed and
inconsequential version of &lt;a class=&quot;reference external&quot; href=&quot;http://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pascal's_wager&quot;&gt;Pascal’s Gambit&lt;/a&gt;.  I know full well that the works
I’ve rejected have been seen to completion by others.  I’ve not scuppered them,
nor have I even attempted to.  Not having me work on them has perhaps even made
them far more effective at whatever aspect I took exception to.  I’m making
moral decisions with no weight beyond my own mind, no ripple beyond my own
insignificant life puddle and no wake beyond this now excessively long essay.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, in the face of these realisations I still find myself unable to
consider the decisions wrong.  I’d still choose to reject them now, and
I suspect that will remain true in the future.  I like that these decisions are
defensible to &lt;em&gt;me&lt;/em&gt;, that they &lt;em&gt;must&lt;/em&gt; be defensible to me.  I love that the thing
that keeps me awake at night is not the thought of the possibly nefarious
effects of my works, but rather the exceedingly minor issue of not having
a glistening and well-spec’d M6 in the garage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, let me sleep.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;rubric&quot;&gt;Footnotes&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;dl class=&quot;footnote brackets&quot;&gt;
&lt;dt class=&quot;label&quot; id=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;brackets&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;fn-backref&quot; href=&quot;#id1&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;&lt;p&gt;For those values to be strong doesn’t necessarily mean they have to
line up with your definition of “strong moral values” ;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="https://jnrowe.github.io/blog/tag/life/atom.xml">
    <title type="text">Tell me a nice story, please</title>
    <id>https://jnrowe.github.io/thoughts/nice_stories.html</id>
    <updated>2013-12-23T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <published>2013-12-23T00:00:00Z</published>
    <link href="https://jnrowe.github.io/thoughts/nice_stories.html" />
    <author>
      <name>James Rowe</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;section&quot; id=&quot;tell-me-a-nice-story-please&quot;&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m fed up of hearing bad stories, I really am.  Often it feels like every
person I know simply revels in the misfortune or missteps of others, and it is
beginning to truly annoy me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can’t work out if it is the result of malicious envy, angry spitefulness or
just a sad realisation that those stories seem to engage others more easily.
That said I don’t believe the reason matters, it is wrong and it needs to stop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&quot;epigraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;You cannot strengthen one by weakening another; and you cannot add to the
stature of a dwarf by cutting off the leg of a giant&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;attribution&quot;&gt;—Benjamin Franklin Fairless&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;section&quot; id=&quot;in-examples&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;In examples&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hmm, this is hard.  How does one express examples without explicitly re-telling
the nasty stories?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The stories you are about to hear are true.  The scenes have been munged to
protect the innocent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;section&quot; id=&quot;exhibit-a&quot;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Exhibit A&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;About five years ago I found out that an old school friend had made a serious,
yet possibly singular, morally irresponsible mistake.  This is a man who was
close to the top of his chosen career tree, with a string of impressive
achievements to his name.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The thing that bugged me about it, and to this day it is still does, is that I’d
never heard anyone remark on his successes prior to this.  I was &lt;em&gt;entirely&lt;/em&gt;
unaware of how his life had turned out prior to this story, and I was completely
unaware of any of the success he had made for himself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, the moment there is a tale with the sprinkled essence of schadenfreude
it felt like you couldn’t go a week without being told about it.  People would
post about it on social-network-du-jour, drop it in to unrelated conversations
and literally stop you in the street to tell you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Why couldn’t I have heard a fantastic story about an old friend’s success when
trying to feed my shocking biscuit habit at Sainsbury’s?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;section&quot; id=&quot;exhibit-b&quot;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Exhibit B&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the mid-naughties a conference friend sold his web service for an apparently
healthy chunk of change.  I remember bumping in to the founding team at a boring
conference and listening to their happiness at the outcome.  They were looking
forward to working on the service itself more, and removing some of the
day-to-day woes of running the business on fumes.  All seemed good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That same day we, along with a bunch of ten or so others, headed off for lunch.
We got to hear some interesting war stories, and some fun tales of moments when
they were writing their “service suicide” notes.  The end of the lunch arrives,
and they decided to pick up the whole tab.  An absolutely unnecessary gesture
given that most, if not all, of us were expensed for the day anyway.  They did
it simply because they’re nice guys.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we started to break up and head back I noticed a few people were now telling
other stories.  Some had heard that the specific amount of money wasn’t worth
the grief, others expressed doubts the site would live on post acquisition, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hadn’t realised initially, but this change in tone appeared to happen almost
the moment the founders left.  Friends who had found success, regaled us with
their stories and kindly paid for our semi-liquid lunch were suddenly being
beaten down for their apparent success.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Why can’t people just find some happiness in the happiness of others?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;section&quot; id=&quot;what-to-do&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What to do&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m not perfect, well not quite anyway ;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If I wasn’t so terribly, terribly ill today I’d be preparing to head to our
Winterval shutdown party.  You’d no doubt find I like to have a little gossip
and moan about things I shouldn’t, and I might even commit a couple of the faux
pas I’ve mentioned above.  Yes, that upsets me. It really does, but I’m trying
to change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;section&quot; id=&quot;a-pledge&quot;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;A pledge&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you catch me using the failure of others for entertainment or to make
a point, feel free to berate me for it.  It might even be time to start offering
fantastic prizes&lt;a class=&quot;footnote-reference brackets&quot; href=&quot;#s1&quot; id=&quot;id1&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt; to people who catch me doing so, as it is probably the only
way I’ll really learn.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;section&quot; id=&quot;what-i-want-to-hear&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What I want to hear&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Simply tell me about that friend who is getting married, don’t tell the story
by mentioning that it is their third marriage.  I also don’t need to hear about
that messy relationship breakdown.  [The exception — of course — being if it is
that one girl who I’d sell my soul for a second chance with]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tell me about that friend whose child aced the &lt;a class=&quot;reference external&quot; href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eleven_plus_exam&quot;&gt;Eleven Plus&lt;/a&gt;, and has been
accepted in to the school we all wish we had attended.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tell me about that old school friend who is building their own &lt;a class=&quot;reference external&quot; href=&quot;http://www.channel4.com/programmes/grand-designs&quot;&gt;Grand
Designs&lt;/a&gt;-esque house.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I guess there is one reason I want to hear the bad stories, and it is very
simple.  &lt;em&gt;Iff&lt;/em&gt; there is some actionable thing I can do to help, then I &lt;em&gt;want&lt;/em&gt; to
know about it.  If that isn’t the case, just keep it to yourself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;rubric&quot;&gt;Footnotes&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;dl class=&quot;footnote brackets&quot;&gt;
&lt;dt class=&quot;label&quot; id=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;brackets&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;fn-backref&quot; href=&quot;#id1&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;&lt;p&gt;Okay, probably just a coffee or a beer&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
