<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title type="text">JNRowe - Posted in 2013</title>
  <id>https://jnrowe.github.io/blog/2013/atom.xml</id>
  <updated>2013-12-23T00:00:00Z</updated>
  <link href="https://jnrowe.github.io/" />
  <link href="https://jnrowe.github.io/blog/2013/atom.xml" rel="self" />
  <subtitle type="text">Ramblings of a tired mind</subtitle>
  <generator uri="http://ablog.readthedocs.org" version="0.9.4">ABlog</generator>
  <entry xml:base="https://jnrowe.github.io/blog/2013/atom.xml">
    <title type="text">Tell me a nice story, please</title>
    <id>https://jnrowe.github.io/thoughts/nice_stories.html</id>
    <updated>2013-12-23T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <published>2013-12-23T00:00:00Z</published>
    <link href="https://jnrowe.github.io/thoughts/nice_stories.html" />
    <author>
      <name>James Rowe</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;section&quot; id=&quot;tell-me-a-nice-story-please&quot;&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m fed up of hearing bad stories, I really am.  Often it feels like every
person I know simply revels in the misfortune or missteps of others, and it is
beginning to truly annoy me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can’t work out if it is the result of malicious envy, angry spitefulness or
just a sad realisation that those stories seem to engage others more easily.
That said I don’t believe the reason matters, it is wrong and it needs to stop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&quot;epigraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;You cannot strengthen one by weakening another; and you cannot add to the
stature of a dwarf by cutting off the leg of a giant&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;attribution&quot;&gt;—Benjamin Franklin Fairless&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;section&quot; id=&quot;in-examples&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;In examples&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hmm, this is hard.  How does one express examples without explicitly re-telling
the nasty stories?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The stories you are about to hear are true.  The scenes have been munged to
protect the innocent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;section&quot; id=&quot;exhibit-a&quot;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Exhibit A&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;About five years ago I found out that an old school friend had made a serious,
yet possibly singular, morally irresponsible mistake.  This is a man who was
close to the top of his chosen career tree, with a string of impressive
achievements to his name.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The thing that bugged me about it, and to this day it is still does, is that I’d
never heard anyone remark on his successes prior to this.  I was &lt;em&gt;entirely&lt;/em&gt;
unaware of how his life had turned out prior to this story, and I was completely
unaware of any of the success he had made for himself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, the moment there is a tale with the sprinkled essence of schadenfreude
it felt like you couldn’t go a week without being told about it.  People would
post about it on social-network-du-jour, drop it in to unrelated conversations
and literally stop you in the street to tell you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Why couldn’t I have heard a fantastic story about an old friend’s success when
trying to feed my shocking biscuit habit at Sainsbury’s?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;section&quot; id=&quot;exhibit-b&quot;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Exhibit B&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the mid-naughties a conference friend sold his web service for an apparently
healthy chunk of change.  I remember bumping in to the founding team at a boring
conference and listening to their happiness at the outcome.  They were looking
forward to working on the service itself more, and removing some of the
day-to-day woes of running the business on fumes.  All seemed good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That same day we, along with a bunch of ten or so others, headed off for lunch.
We got to hear some interesting war stories, and some fun tales of moments when
they were writing their “service suicide” notes.  The end of the lunch arrives,
and they decided to pick up the whole tab.  An absolutely unnecessary gesture
given that most, if not all, of us were expensed for the day anyway.  They did
it simply because they’re nice guys.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we started to break up and head back I noticed a few people were now telling
other stories.  Some had heard that the specific amount of money wasn’t worth
the grief, others expressed doubts the site would live on post acquisition, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hadn’t realised initially, but this change in tone appeared to happen almost
the moment the founders left.  Friends who had found success, regaled us with
their stories and kindly paid for our semi-liquid lunch were suddenly being
beaten down for their apparent success.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Why can’t people just find some happiness in the happiness of others?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;section&quot; id=&quot;what-to-do&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What to do&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m not perfect, well not quite anyway ;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If I wasn’t so terribly, terribly ill today I’d be preparing to head to our
Winterval shutdown party.  You’d no doubt find I like to have a little gossip
and moan about things I shouldn’t, and I might even commit a couple of the faux
pas I’ve mentioned above.  Yes, that upsets me. It really does, but I’m trying
to change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;section&quot; id=&quot;a-pledge&quot;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;A pledge&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you catch me using the failure of others for entertainment or to make
a point, feel free to berate me for it.  It might even be time to start offering
fantastic prizes&lt;a class=&quot;footnote-reference brackets&quot; href=&quot;#s1&quot; id=&quot;id1&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt; to people who catch me doing so, as it is probably the only
way I’ll really learn.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;section&quot; id=&quot;what-i-want-to-hear&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What I want to hear&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Simply tell me about that friend who is getting married, don’t tell the story
by mentioning that it is their third marriage.  I also don’t need to hear about
that messy relationship breakdown.  [The exception — of course — being if it is
that one girl who I’d sell my soul for a second chance with]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tell me about that friend whose child aced the &lt;a class=&quot;reference external&quot; href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eleven_plus_exam&quot;&gt;Eleven Plus&lt;/a&gt;, and has been
accepted in to the school we all wish we had attended.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tell me about that old school friend who is building their own &lt;a class=&quot;reference external&quot; href=&quot;http://www.channel4.com/programmes/grand-designs&quot;&gt;Grand
Designs&lt;/a&gt;-esque house.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I guess there is one reason I want to hear the bad stories, and it is very
simple.  &lt;em&gt;Iff&lt;/em&gt; there is some actionable thing I can do to help, then I &lt;em&gt;want&lt;/em&gt; to
know about it.  If that isn’t the case, just keep it to yourself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;rubric&quot;&gt;Footnotes&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;dl class=&quot;footnote brackets&quot;&gt;
&lt;dt class=&quot;label&quot; id=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;brackets&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;fn-backref&quot; href=&quot;#id1&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;&lt;p&gt;Okay, probably just a coffee or a beer&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="https://jnrowe.github.io/blog/2013/atom.xml">
    <title type="text">Side-projects</title>
    <id>https://jnrowe.github.io/thoughts/side_projects.html</id>
    <updated>2013-12-16T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <published>2013-12-16T00:00:00Z</published>
    <link href="https://jnrowe.github.io/thoughts/side_projects.html" />
    <author>
      <name>James Rowe</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;section&quot; id=&quot;side-projects&quot;&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chatting with my brother yesterday he expressed some disbelief when I mentioned
&lt;em&gt;yet another&lt;/em&gt; friend who has a website related to some topic we were discussing:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Does everyone you know run a website?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes, yes, they do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It hadn’t really occurred to me until I was reading a write up of a co-workers
weekend hack.  The majority of nerdy people I know run websites, create
iPhone/android apps or have other side projects in various states of completion.
It’s just How Things Work®&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I guess it is mostly a cultural issue, one which is quite strong behind the
engineering side of the curtain in my workplace.  Sure, there are some “5:01”
types who are out of the door as soon as the bell rings, but there are an awful
lot who extend their tech creations in to a downtime hobby or side business.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To relate this to my brother I think of a family party we attended this past
weekend.  When people asked me what my brother does I’d say that he works in
logistics, and the conversation drifts from there.  When talking to the
extended family that often seemed to head toward being about material
possessions that work may afford him.  However, I’ve noticed in the past when
I’m talking to people I’d call friends it often quickly digresses in to strange
discussions about box packing, routing, &lt;a class=&quot;reference external&quot; href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Travelling_salesman_problem&quot;&gt;the curse of travelling salesmen&lt;/a&gt; or
&lt;a class=&quot;reference external&quot; href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bridges_of_Konigsberg&quot;&gt;bridges in some foreign land&lt;/a&gt;.  Because of the math and technology
implications many of my friends have written tools to explore some of the
practical and theoretical issues faced in logistics… often for fun.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;section&quot; id=&quot;it-is-all-about-me&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;It is all about me&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m not working on any public facing websites right now&lt;a class=&quot;footnote-reference brackets&quot; href=&quot;#s1&quot; id=&quot;id1&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;, but I do play
with a few public facing projects from time to time that should head towards
proving my point.  I’m picking a few semi-randomly to illustrate a little
diversity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;admonition note&quot;&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;admonition-title&quot;&gt;Note&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To save myself some researching effort I’ll only link to things from &lt;a class=&quot;reference external&quot; href=&quot;https://github.com/JNRowe/&quot;&gt;my
GitHub profile&lt;/a&gt; or links from my browser’s bookmarks, but that should be
descriptive enough to get the point across.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;section&quot; id=&quot;gentoo-packages&quot;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Gentoo packages&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the past decade I’ve spent a lot of time hacking on things related to
&lt;a class=&quot;reference external&quot; href=&quot;http://gentoo.org/&quot;&gt;Gentoo&lt;/a&gt;.  Some of that for work projects and some of it for &lt;a class=&quot;reference external&quot; href=&quot;https://jnrowe-misc.readthedocs.io/&quot;&gt;personal
projects&lt;/a&gt;.  I’ve also experienced my fair share of troubles, and have &lt;a class=&quot;reference external&quot; href=&quot;https://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?email1=jnrowe%40gmail.com&amp;amp;emailassigned_to1=1&amp;amp;emailcc1=1&amp;amp;emaillongdesc1=1&amp;amp;emailreporter1=1&amp;amp;emailtype1=substring&amp;amp;query_format=advanced&quot;&gt;reported
a few bugs&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At one time I even hoped to &lt;a class=&quot;reference external&quot; href=&quot;https://bugs.gentoo.org/show_bug.cgi?id=142090&quot;&gt;become a developer&lt;/a&gt;, but that didn’t work out for
a bunch of reasons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;section&quot; id=&quot;github2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;docutils literal notranslate&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pre&quot;&gt;github2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a year I &lt;a class=&quot;reference external&quot; href=&quot;https://github.com/ask/python-github2/graphs/contributors&quot;&gt;maintained&lt;/a&gt; a relatively popular &lt;a class=&quot;reference external&quot; href=&quot;https://github.com/ask/python-github2&quot;&gt;API wrapper&lt;/a&gt; to GitHub.  I did
this because I found it fun.  It provided no economic benefit to me, and I never
expected it to.  I know a lot of people used it when building their own toy
projects and websites, because many were kind enough to link to it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;section&quot; id=&quot;pyisbn&quot;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;docutils literal notranslate&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pre&quot;&gt;pyisbn&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For seven years I’ve maintained a small library for &lt;a class=&quot;reference external&quot; href=&quot;https://github.com/JNRowe/pyisbn/&quot;&gt;validating ISBNs&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;em&gt;Yes, that is absolutely as boring as it sounds&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was never meant to be used by others, I just needed something to validate
entries in my e-book database.  Other people started using it, many for their
own weird side projects including a number of book retail websites.  It has
amassed literally tens of thousands of downloads from &lt;abbr title=&quot;Python Package Index&quot;&gt;PyPI&lt;/abbr&gt;, but you really
shouldn’t trust the dubious statistics from &lt;abbr title=&quot;Python Package Index&quot;&gt;PyPI&lt;/abbr&gt; ;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;section&quot; id=&quot;rdial&quot;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;docutils literal notranslate&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pre&quot;&gt;rdial&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;docutils literal notranslate&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pre&quot;&gt;rdial&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; is a &lt;a class=&quot;reference external&quot; href=&quot;https://rdial.readthedocs.io/&quot;&gt;time tracking tool&lt;/a&gt;, and a perfect example for me.  I played
with it for over a year before anyone else saw it, just because it scratched an
itch I had.  I never imagined it would be useful to others.  Turns out it was,
and there is now a small yet faithful band of users.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I even received the great honour of a few summer evening beers for releasing it.
A beer being second only to a patch in the table of project endorsements
that I subscribe to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;section&quot; id=&quot;upoints-nee-earth-distance&quot;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;docutils literal notranslate&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pre&quot;&gt;upoints&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; née &lt;code class=&quot;docutils literal notranslate&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pre&quot;&gt;earth_distance&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;reference external&quot; href=&quot;https://jnrowe.github.io/upoints/&quot;&gt;upoints&lt;/a&gt; is a strange one.  It started as a &lt;a class=&quot;reference external&quot; href=&quot;http://jnrowe.github.io/upoints/geolocation_and_pathcross.html&quot;&gt;stupid hack&lt;/a&gt; to figure out some
silly travel planning drama, it proceeded to take on a life of its own.  Over
the years it attracted a fair amount of users, and I still receive email about
it now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It did have some tangible benefit though, the sadly now defunct website it
eventually spawned opened some nice doors for me.  I didn’t know it would or
could at the time, so it didn’t affect how I spent my time when playing with it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;section&quot; id=&quot;cut-from-the-pattern&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Cut from the pattern&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This isn’t specific to me, or even to the particularly nerdy among my
co-workers.  If you &lt;a class=&quot;reference external&quot; href=&quot;https://github.com/explore&quot;&gt;dig around on GitHub&lt;/a&gt;, or even &lt;a class=&quot;reference external&quot; href=&quot;http://makezine.com/&quot;&gt;makezine&lt;/a&gt;, you’ll see
people creating purely because they can.  This isn’t a new phenomenon either.
If you were around pre-GitHub you’d see people making things on Sourceforge.  If
you were around before Sourceforge, you’ll remember the good old days when life
was simpler and people held doors open for you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The point is simple.  Yes, I &lt;em&gt;may&lt;/em&gt; know someone who is working on
project/website related to some topic, but that is only because many of the
people I know are spitting out new projects on what often appears to be a weekly
basis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;rubric&quot;&gt;Footnotes&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;dl class=&quot;footnote brackets&quot;&gt;
&lt;dt class=&quot;label&quot; id=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;brackets&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;fn-backref&quot; href=&quot;#id1&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;&lt;p&gt;I really don’t count &lt;a class=&quot;reference external&quot; href=&quot;http://jnrowe.github.io/&quot;&gt;this site&lt;/a&gt;, as it
is just a jumbled content dump with no real purpose.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
