<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>https://jnrowe.github.io/</id>
  <title>JNRowe - Posts tagged gps</title>
  <updated>2021-03-29T21:43:24.074002+00:00</updated>
  <link href="https://jnrowe.github.io/"/>
  <link href="https://jnrowe.github.io/blog/tag/gps/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <generator uri="https://ablog.readthedocs.org/" version="0.10.17">ABlog</generator>
  <subtitle>Ramblings of a tired mind</subtitle>
  <entry>
    <id>https://jnrowe.github.io/articles/gps_rollover_2019.html</id>
    <title>GPS rollover 2019</title>
    <updated>2019-04-05T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>James Rowe</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="section" id="gps-rollover-2019"&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tomorrow we’re going to experience the simultaneously cataclysmic and mundane
consequences of a &lt;abbr title="Global Positioning System"&gt;GPS&lt;/abbr&gt; rollover event.  &lt;em&gt;Many&lt;/em&gt; things will break, &lt;em&gt;many&lt;/em&gt; will
continue to work and &lt;em&gt;many&lt;/em&gt; will just take a step closer to breaking… the fun
of date handling never ends.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="Pick a year, win a prize" class="align-right" src="../../_images/gps_calendar.png" /&gt;
&lt;div class="admonition note"&gt;
&lt;p class="admonition-title"&gt;Note&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is an informal piece, not an official support channel.  If you use
hardware I’m involved in building then contact your support channel, they
are there to help.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="what-is-the-issue"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What is the issue?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since 1981 &lt;abbr title="Global Positioning System"&gt;GPS&lt;/abbr&gt; signals have included a week number, which is provided as
a 10-bit field and as such can only store 1024 values(around 19.5 years).
Every time we hit that limit the week number rolls back to zero, and things may
fail to work correctly following that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="sidebar"&gt;
&lt;p class="sidebar-title"&gt;Prior to ‘81&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a side note very early &lt;abbr title="Global Positioning System"&gt;GPS&lt;/abbr&gt; transmissions didn’t even include week
numbers in the signal.  Time was represented simply as a value &lt;em&gt;within&lt;/em&gt;
a week, and not &lt;em&gt;belonging&lt;/em&gt; to a week.  If you work in the industry you
still occasionally come across implementations that work like this, or
issues that are caused by this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There have been a surprising number of other largely backward compatible
upgrades to the &lt;abbr title="Global Positioning System"&gt;GPS&lt;/abbr&gt; signal over the approaching fifty years of its
development.  Coupled with the out of band enhancements such as &lt;abbr title="Wide Area Augmentation System"&gt;WAAS&lt;/abbr&gt;, the accuracy and uses of &lt;abbr title="Global Positioning System"&gt;GPS&lt;/abbr&gt;-based
systems have increased a tremendous amount.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the second operational rollover event, the first happened in August
1999.  We — that is developers of &lt;abbr title="Global Navigation Satellite System"&gt;GNSS&lt;/abbr&gt;-using systems — &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; prepared for
this, but the level of preparedness is unfortunately not uniform or indicative
of how well we’re handling this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="mitigations"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Mitigations&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As this problem is quite well understood there has been an awful lot of effort
put in to working around it, some quite simple and some quite interesting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="stored-offset"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Stored offset&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The gold standard is systems that could afford the addition of &lt;abbr title="Non-Volatile Random Access Memory"&gt;NVRAM&lt;/abbr&gt;.  If we have a storage medium then the
previous known week number is often used as a check against rollover.  If we
know an initial epoch number from manufacturing date, and can see the
changeover at &lt;em&gt;some&lt;/em&gt; point than you &lt;em&gt;shouldn’t&lt;/em&gt; experience errors from
a rollover.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The obvious drawback being if a system is dormant for twenty years, but that
isn’t likely to be a real problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="week-number-offset"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Week number offset&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the most common mechanisms for dealing with rollover has been to bind it
to the firmware running on the device.  You simply assume the week number is
relative to a value given in the firmware.  For example, if we have firmware
from 2010 we can:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Assume we’re not running in 1999 via a time machine&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Know we can’t see week numbers prior to our 2010 release date&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Accept the given week number as valid through to 1023&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;After rollover treat week number 0 through 540 as being an offset past 1023&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a reasonable solution in many circumstances, and one that exists in
many products in the field.  It also hints at part of the problem with this
method, and that is that a significant number of systems that will present
problems at various stages of their lives.  In the above example our system
&lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; work through the epoch change in 2019, but will likely fail in August
2029 without intervention as we’ll trip over &lt;em&gt;our&lt;/em&gt; workaround with our own
rollover bug causing it to reset to 2010.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="gnss-voting-comparisons"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;abbr title="Global Navigation Satellite System"&gt;GNSS&lt;/abbr&gt; voting comparisons&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many modern receivers support multiple signals; &lt;abbr title="Global Positioning System"&gt;GPS&lt;/abbr&gt;, GLONASS, Beidou, &amp;amp;c.
Given this we can use consensus building to validate information.  If one of
the inputs is providing time data that is years away from the others you can
simply exclude it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="admonition tip"&gt;
&lt;p class="admonition-title"&gt;Tip&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Often systems may have alternative time sources available such as a regular
low quality &lt;abbr title="Real Time Clock"&gt;RTC&lt;/abbr&gt;, these can also be used as a hint
towards consensus building too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="leap-second-heuristic"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Leap second heuristic&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;abbr title="Global Positioning System"&gt;GPS&lt;/abbr&gt; time is not corrected for leap seconds and as such increasingly drifts
from &lt;abbr title="Coordinated Universal Time"&gt;UTC&lt;/abbr&gt; over the years.  However, the current offset from &lt;abbr title="Coordinated Universal Time"&gt;UTC&lt;/abbr&gt; is
transmitted, and it can be used as an heuristic to configure the device from.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, when the first epoch ended in 1999 there was a 13 second offset
against &lt;abbr title="Coordinated Universal Time"&gt;UTC&lt;/abbr&gt;.  The switch to the third epoch happens with an 18 second offset.
Keying the epoch number off of the leap second offset &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; be a reasonable
way to handle rollover&lt;a class="footnote-reference brackets" href="#id3" id="id1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Forthcoming leap second adjustments are also published, so we can know both
the current offset and the maximum date given that future dates must be in the
future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="admonition note"&gt;
&lt;p class="admonition-title"&gt;Note&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Leap second information is only published within &lt;abbr title="Global Positioning System"&gt;GPS&lt;/abbr&gt; almanac, and is not
available immediately following a cold boot of a device.  Depending on
circumstances the 12 minute wait to acquire the almanac data may not be an
issue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="what-should-i-do"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What should I do?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First check with your system’s supplier, they &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; have information on what
mitigations they have in place and what effects you should see now or at other
times in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next step should be to &lt;em&gt;ignore&lt;/em&gt; what they told you and run a signal
simulator to figure out what is actually happening.  Date handling bugs happen
in so many layers you should have a testing procedure in place regardless of
your trust in a supplier&lt;a class="footnote-reference brackets" href="#id4" id="id2"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="admonition warning"&gt;
&lt;p class="admonition-title"&gt;Warning&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fully read the documentation for simulators and receivers as many devices
require a deep reset to make use of a simulated signal.  The P3200 sitting
on my desk requires a hardware switch to be toggled before it will do
anything beyond report “spoofing detected” if it receives unexpected
signals, with the exception of a &lt;abbr title="Trust On First Use"&gt;TOFU&lt;/abbr&gt; event
following a deep reset.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="should-i-set-an-alarm-for-november-2038"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Should I set an alarm for November 2038?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes and no.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next rollover will occur in 2038, but new message types that use a 13-bit
week number field are available and increasingly being used.  This enhancement
changes the cycle to nearly 157 years, so we can naïvely hope this shouldn’t be
an issue again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, there &lt;em&gt;will&lt;/em&gt; be systems that are still in the field that were
developed prior to the upgrade and there &lt;em&gt;will&lt;/em&gt; be systems that were designed
later that still use the old 10-bit field for their week data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like I said in the previous section make sure you’re testing these things as
they’ll catch you out at some point.  Maybe even in fun ways such as exciting
interactions between the fourth GPS epoch and the &lt;em&gt;other&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Y2038_problem"&gt;2038 problem&lt;/a&gt; in
January of that same year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="rubric"&gt;Footnotes&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;dl class="footnote brackets"&gt;
&lt;dt class="label" id="id3"&gt;&lt;span class="brackets"&gt;&lt;a class="fn-backref" href="#id1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;&lt;p&gt;We’re assuming the earth doesn’t suddenly speed up enough that we need
to start issuing negative leap seconds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt class="label" id="id4"&gt;&lt;span class="brackets"&gt;&lt;a class="fn-backref" href="#id2"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;&lt;p&gt;I’m &lt;em&gt;absolutely&lt;/em&gt; including products worked on by myself and my
co-workers(forgive me!) in this.  People make mistakes, systems fail and
skies may fall; having a good testing infrastructure is a must.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
    <link href="https://jnrowe.github.io/articles/gps_rollover_2019.html" rel="alternate"/>
    <category term="gps" label="gps"/>
    <category term="time" label="time"/>
    <category term="bugs" label="bugs"/>
    <published>2019-04-05T00:00:00+01:00</published>
  </entry>
</feed>
