<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>https://jnrowe.github.io/</id>
  <title>JNRowe - Posts tagged projects</title>
  <updated>2018-12-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
  <link href="https://jnrowe.github.io/"/>
  <link href="https://jnrowe.github.io/blog/tag/projects/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <generator uri="https://ablog.readthedocs.org/" version="0.10.23">ABlog</generator>
  <subtitle>Ramblings of a tired mind</subtitle>
  <entry>
    <id>https://jnrowe.github.io/thoughts/side_projects.html</id>
    <title>Side-projects</title>
    <updated>2013-12-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>James Rowe</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;section id="side-projects"&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chatting with my brother yesterday he expressed some disbelief when I mentioned
&lt;em&gt;yet another&lt;/em&gt; friend who has a website related to some topic we were discussing:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Does everyone you know run a website?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes, yes, they do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It hadn’t really occurred to me until I was reading a write up of a co-workers
weekend hack.  The majority of nerdy people I know run websites, create
iPhone/android apps or have other side projects in various states of completion.
It’s just How Things Work®&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I guess it is mostly a cultural issue, one which is quite strong behind the
engineering side of the curtain in my workplace.  Sure, there are some “5:01”
types who are out of the door as soon as the bell rings, but there are an awful
lot who extend their tech creations in to a downtime hobby or side business.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To relate this to my brother I think of a family party we attended this past
weekend.  When people asked me what my brother does I’d say that he works in
logistics, and the conversation drifts from there.  When talking to the
extended family that often seemed to head toward being about material
possessions that work may afford him.  However, I’ve noticed in the past when
I’m talking to people I’d call friends it often quickly digresses in to strange
discussions about box packing, routing, &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Travelling_salesman_problem"&gt;the curse of travelling salesmen&lt;/a&gt; or
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bridges_of_Konigsberg"&gt;bridges in some foreign land&lt;/a&gt;.  Because of the math and technology
implications many of my friends have written tools to explore some of the
practical and theoretical issues faced in logistics… often for fun.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section id="it-is-all-about-me"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;It is all about me&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m not working on any public facing websites right now&lt;a class="footnote-reference brackets" href="#s1" id="id1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;, but I do play
with a few public facing projects from time to time that should head towards
proving my point.  I’m picking a few semi-randomly to illustrate a little
diversity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="admonition note"&gt;
&lt;p class="admonition-title"&gt;Note&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To save myself some researching effort I’ll only link to things from &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/JNRowe/"&gt;my
GitHub profile&lt;/a&gt; or links from my browser’s bookmarks, but that should be
descriptive enough to get the point across.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;section id="gentoo-packages"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Gentoo packages&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the past decade I’ve spent a lot of time hacking on things related to
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://gentoo.org/"&gt;Gentoo&lt;/a&gt;.  Some of that for work projects and some of it for &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://jnrowe-misc.readthedocs.io/"&gt;personal
projects&lt;/a&gt;.  I’ve also experienced my fair share of troubles, and have &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?email1=jnrowe%40gmail.com&amp;amp;emailassigned_to1=1&amp;amp;emailcc1=1&amp;amp;emaillongdesc1=1&amp;amp;emailreporter1=1&amp;amp;emailtype1=substring&amp;amp;query_format=advanced"&gt;reported
a few bugs&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At one time I even hoped to &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://bugs.gentoo.org/show_bug.cgi?id=142090"&gt;become a developer&lt;/a&gt;, but that didn’t work out for
a bunch of reasons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="github2"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;github2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a year I &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/ask/python-github2/graphs/contributors"&gt;maintained&lt;/a&gt; a relatively popular &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/ask/python-github2"&gt;API wrapper&lt;/a&gt; to GitHub.  I did
this because I found it fun.  It provided no economic benefit to me, and I never
expected it to.  I know a lot of people used it when building their own toy
projects and websites, because many were kind enough to link to it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="pyisbn"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;pyisbn&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For seven years I’ve maintained a small library for &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/JNRowe/pyisbn/"&gt;validating ISBNs&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;em&gt;Yes, that is absolutely as boring as it sounds&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was never meant to be used by others, I just needed something to validate
entries in my e-book database.  Other people started using it, many for their
own weird side projects including a number of book retail websites.  It has
amassed literally tens of thousands of downloads from &lt;abbr title="Python Package Index"&gt;PyPI&lt;/abbr&gt;, but you really
shouldn’t trust the dubious statistics from &lt;abbr title="Python Package Index"&gt;PyPI&lt;/abbr&gt; ;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="rdial"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;rdial&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;rdial&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; is a &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://rdial.readthedocs.io/"&gt;time tracking tool&lt;/a&gt;, and a perfect example for me.  I played
with it for over a year before anyone else saw it, just because it scratched an
itch I had.  I never imagined it would be useful to others.  Turns out it was,
and there is now a small yet faithful band of users.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I even received the great honour of a few summer evening beers for releasing it.
A beer being second only to a patch in the table of project endorsements
that I subscribe to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="upoints-nee-earth-distance"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;upoints&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; née &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;earth_distance&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://jnrowe.github.io/upoints/"&gt;upoints&lt;/a&gt; is a strange one.  It started as a &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://jnrowe.github.io/upoints/geolocation_and_pathcross.html"&gt;stupid hack&lt;/a&gt; to figure out some
silly travel planning drama, it proceeded to take on a life of its own.  Over
the years it attracted a fair amount of users, and I still receive email about
it now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It did have some tangible benefit though, the sadly now defunct website it
eventually spawned opened some nice doors for me.  I didn’t know it would or
could at the time, so it didn’t affect how I spent my time when playing with it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="cut-from-the-pattern"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Cut from the pattern&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This isn’t specific to me, or even to the particularly nerdy among my
co-workers.  If you &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/explore"&gt;dig around on GitHub&lt;/a&gt;, or even &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://makezine.com/"&gt;makezine&lt;/a&gt;, you’ll see
people creating purely because they can.  This isn’t a new phenomenon either.
If you were around pre-GitHub you’d see people making things on Sourceforge.  If
you were around before Sourceforge, you’ll remember the good old days when life
was simpler and people held doors open for you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The point is simple.  Yes, I &lt;em&gt;may&lt;/em&gt; know someone who is working on
project/website related to some topic, but that is only because many of the
people I know are spitting out new projects on what often appears to be a weekly
basis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="rubric"&gt;Footnotes&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;dl class="footnote brackets"&gt;
&lt;dt class="label" id="s1"&gt;&lt;span class="brackets"&gt;&lt;a class="fn-backref" href="#id1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;&lt;p&gt;I really don’t count &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://jnrowe.github.io/"&gt;this site&lt;/a&gt;, as it
is just a jumbled content dump with no real purpose.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="https://jnrowe.github.io/thoughts/side_projects.html" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>Chatting with my brother yesterday he expressed some disbelief when I mentioned
yet another friend who has a website related to some topic we were discussing:</summary>
    <category term="hobbies" label="hobbies"/>
    <category term="projects" label="projects"/>
    <published>2013-12-16T00:00:00+00:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://jnrowe.github.io/articles/fossil.html</id>
    <title>fossil experiments</title>
    <updated>2014-11-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>James Rowe</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;section id="fossil-experiments"&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a variety of reasons we can no longer use GitHub at work for any project
which isn’t Open Source.  And since that decision was thrust upon us we’ve been
playing with some alternatives for our workflow.  We’ll probably end up choosing
one of the self hosted clones at some point, but it was decided early on that we
should evaluate a variety of options.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was tasked with testing out &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.fossil-scm.org/"&gt;fossil&lt;/a&gt; on a couple of small side projects, and
these are my &lt;em&gt;absolutely&lt;/em&gt; biased personal findings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before I start I should add that while what I’m about to write probably sounds
harsh, I do like &lt;strong class="command"&gt;fossil&lt;/strong&gt; the concept.  I like the single &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://sqlite.org/"&gt;sqlite&lt;/a&gt;
project repository, I like the small-enough-to-grok-in-an-afternoon code base
and I like the idea of a totally reproducible project state including all
metadata.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section id="testing-fossil"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Testing &lt;strong class="command"&gt;fossil&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The good news is that testing &lt;strong class="command"&gt;fossil&lt;/strong&gt; is a piece of cake.  It
supports both reading and writing &lt;strong class="command"&gt;git&lt;/strong&gt;’s &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://git-scm.com/docs/git-fast-import"&gt;fast-import&lt;/a&gt; format.  If you
want to test it out just dump an existing &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.git-scm.com/"&gt;git&lt;/a&gt; repository(or &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://mercurial.selenic.com/wiki/FastImportExtension"&gt;mercurial with an
extension&lt;/a&gt;), and feed it &lt;strong class="command"&gt;fossil import&lt;/strong&gt;.  If you later change your
mind you can run &lt;strong class="command"&gt;fossil export&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sadly supporting incremental two-way mirroring didn’t work out for us, but
perhaps it will for simpler projects.  In the end I simply mirrored the
&lt;strong class="command"&gt;git&lt;/strong&gt; repositories to &lt;strong class="command"&gt;fossil&lt;/strong&gt;, marked the &lt;strong class="command"&gt;git&lt;/strong&gt;
repositories as read-only and forced contributors to work with
&lt;strong class="command"&gt;fossil&lt;/strong&gt; from the outset.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="packaging"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Packaging&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong class="command"&gt;fossil&lt;/strong&gt; project sells itself on being a single file binary
install, and that probably works well for a subset of users.  We’re not that in
that subset though, and &lt;strong class="command"&gt;fossil&lt;/strong&gt; is more than a little annoying to
wrangle in to our environment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The tarball ships without any &lt;em&gt;directly&lt;/em&gt; usable documentation, so you end up
with either no system documentation or a collection of docs sprinkled with wiki
markup in &lt;code class="file docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;/usr/share/doc&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By default &lt;strong class="command"&gt;fossil&lt;/strong&gt; builds in a manner which unfortunately breaks most
packaging standards.  If you’re building packages you’ll likely need to write an
awful lot of custom workarounds to get a compliant and usable package, see
&lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;lst-pkgs/utils/dev/fossil&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; build for the gory details of my hacks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="uptake"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Uptake&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don’t really want to hold this against &lt;strong class="command"&gt;fossil&lt;/strong&gt;, but it &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt;
important to note that for all intents and purposes no one is familiar with it.
No upstream projects we actively track use it, there isn’t a single person who
chooses to use it on our site(which is why I had to handle the packaging) and
expecting new hires to have even heard of it is probably a stretch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It wouldn’t be such an issue if the choice was a &lt;strong class="command"&gt;git&lt;/strong&gt; vs &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://mercurial.selenic.com/"&gt;mercurial&lt;/a&gt;
one, where the few differences are mostly cosmetic.  &lt;strong class="command"&gt;fossil&lt;/strong&gt; is
a completely different beast, and requires an enormous rethink in the way you
handle version control.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ten years ago when people were on the whole still familiar with the &lt;abbr title="Concurrent Versions System"&gt;CVS&lt;/abbr&gt; and
Subversion way of working that wouldn’t have been such an issue, but times have
most definitely changed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The vocabulary in the documentation is likely to be foreign to users of any
version control system, and the workflow examples in the documentation are
entirely foreign to how we have developed any project in at least the past
decade.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="all-in-one-solution"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;All-in-one solution&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the proclaimed benefits of using &lt;strong class="command"&gt;fossil&lt;/strong&gt; is that it handles
many aspects of a project’s &lt;abbr title="Application Lifecycle Management"&gt;ALM&lt;/abbr&gt;; version control, issue tracking,
documentation(via a wiki), etc.  However, and this is only my opinion, it feels
like it does all of these in a suboptimal manner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section id="version-control"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Version control&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The version control feels quite nice for the most part, definitely usable but
a little annoying to work with if you’re used to a modern &lt;abbr title="Distributed Version Control System"&gt;DVCS&lt;/abbr&gt; like we are.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That said it does feel like a &lt;em&gt;huge&lt;/em&gt; step backwards when working with branches,
and you should set aside quite a lot of time for integration issues when you
have &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;autosync&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; disabled.  And I can’t imagine a scenario where &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;autosync&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;
could work for us, without rewriting our entire way of working or returning to
&lt;abbr title="Concurrent Versions System"&gt;CVS&lt;/abbr&gt;-style mega commits and a manual patch stack layered on top.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you read &lt;strong class="command"&gt;fossil&lt;/strong&gt;’s &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.bugzilla.org"&gt;Branching, Forking, Merging, and Tagging&lt;/a&gt;
documentation it appears that this is a design feature for the creators.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="issue-tracker"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Issue tracker&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The issue tracker feels like someone has tried to improve on &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.bugzilla.org"&gt;Bugzilla&lt;/a&gt;, without
taking a look at modern trackers.  It is definitely the weakest part of
&lt;strong class="command"&gt;fossil&lt;/strong&gt; in my opinion, using it is both a mental and eye-stabbing
pain at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luckily you can rework a lot of it by fiddling around with the administration
settings exposed by &lt;strong class="command"&gt;fossil ui&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This also exposes one of the best features of &lt;strong class="command"&gt;fossil&lt;/strong&gt;, you can create
a custom &lt;abbr title="Structured Query Language"&gt;SQL&lt;/abbr&gt; script that configures the project(issue tracking, pretty theme,
etc) and just blast it in to the project’s database.  Or you can create
a custom file that makes all your edits and pump it in with &lt;strong class="command"&gt;fossil
config import&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="wiki"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Wiki&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The wiki system is actually really good for what it does, but it has very few of
the features we use for our documentation.  I don’t want to hold that against it
though, as it just a impedance mismatch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The end result of the integrated components feels to me like you’ve chosen
a usable, but weak, component for some of the most important parts of your
project’s &lt;abbr title="Application Lifecycle Management"&gt;ALM&lt;/abbr&gt;.  The bits work well together, but none of them seem like an
option you’d choose on their own.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="interface"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Interface&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The help output for new users is, in my opinion, really irritating.  The default
command message tells you to run &lt;strong class="command"&gt;fossil help&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;strong class="command"&gt;fossil
help COMMAND&lt;/strong&gt;, without providing the names of any of the common commands.  The
&lt;strong class="command"&gt;fossil help&lt;/strong&gt; output emulates a &lt;strong class="command"&gt;column -t&lt;/strong&gt; filter of the
command names, listing commands with unique to &lt;strong class="command"&gt;fossil&lt;/strong&gt; terminology
and no short descriptions.  &lt;strong class="command"&gt;fossil help --all&lt;/strong&gt; feels like it should
be more useful, but just creates a larger table of commands with uncommon names
and still no descriptions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It makes very little sense to organise the help in this manner because as you
get used to the naming and non-standard option style you will need the help
less.  I’ve patched this for our packages, and if people like it I’ll try to
push it upstream.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="admonition note"&gt;
&lt;p class="admonition-title"&gt;Note&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It turns out I won’t be pushing the changes upstream.  They require
a &lt;abbr title="Contributor License Agreement"&gt;CLA&lt;/abbr&gt; that I can not sign in good faith, which is a shame.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The option handling &lt;em&gt;will&lt;/em&gt; trip you up endlessly.  Just the little things like
being unable to chain options, and needing an endless stream of &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;C-p&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="pre"&gt;M-5&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="pre"&gt;M-b&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="pre"&gt;&amp;lt;space&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; to add a space before a commit message for example.  Yes, I know some
people don’t like standard &lt;strong class="command"&gt;getopt&lt;/strong&gt; or GNU-style option parsing, but
every other tool you use has chosen it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of the interface decisions are actively bad, for example there appears to
be no way to delegate password configuration to a trusted system service or even
&lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;netrc&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;.  Specifying passwords in &lt;abbr title="Uniform Resource Locator"&gt;URL&lt;/abbr&gt;’s on the command line is a &lt;strong&gt;huge&lt;/strong&gt;
anti-pattern, and I just hope you don’t have any multiseat systems if you’re
using that method.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="speed"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Speed&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the whole &lt;strong class="command"&gt;fossil&lt;/strong&gt; is fast, not &lt;strong class="command"&gt;git&lt;/strong&gt; fast but fast
nonetheless.  Commits do take a disturbingly long time to complete for some
reason, but most of the other commands are fast enough.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mangling a repository is actually a lot faster with &lt;strong class="command"&gt;fossil&lt;/strong&gt; than any
other system I can think of, as you can just throw the power of &lt;abbr title="Structured Query Language"&gt;SQL&lt;/abbr&gt; at it.
You can find some &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.sqlalchemy.org/"&gt;sqlalchemy&lt;/a&gt; &lt;abbr title="Object relational mapping"&gt;ORM&lt;/abbr&gt;
definitions in &lt;code class="file docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;/usr/share/doc/fossil/orm&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; in my packages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="conclusion"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I mentioned this in this first paragraph, but I don’t see us moving to
&lt;strong class="command"&gt;fossil&lt;/strong&gt;.  It is a nice system, but it just wouldn’t work for us as
is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Part of me is tempted to attempt to fix the problems, but then we’d be left with
a system that is more obscure than &lt;strong class="command"&gt;fossil&lt;/strong&gt;.  If you read the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://fossil-scm.org/xfer/doc/tip/www/concepts.wiki"&gt;Fossil
Concepts&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.fossil-scm.org/xfer/doc/tip/www/faq.wiki"&gt;Frequently Asked Questions&lt;/a&gt; documents you’ll see that the most
significant problems for us are actually features for upstream, and that is
obviously fine but it does mean upstreaming changes would be impossible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="admonition note"&gt;
&lt;p class="admonition-title"&gt;Note&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As noted above, it turns out they require a &lt;abbr title="Contributor License Agreement"&gt;CLA&lt;/abbr&gt; which means we couldn’t
send changes upstream anyway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That said I’m am planning on stealing some of the ideas that I really liked
about &lt;strong class="command"&gt;fossil&lt;/strong&gt; for my own use.  &lt;strong class="command"&gt;fossil all&lt;/strong&gt;’s ability to run
a command against all repositories configured in &lt;code class="file docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;~/.fossil&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; for example.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="https://jnrowe.github.io/articles/fossil.html" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>For a variety of reasons we can no longer use GitHub at work for any project
which isn’t Open Source.  And since that decision was thrust upon us we’ve been
playing with some alternatives for our workflow.  We’ll probably end up choosing
one of the self hosted clones at some point, but it was decided early on that we
should evaluate a variety of options.</summary>
    <category term="fossil" label="fossil"/>
    <category term="vcs" label="vcs"/>
    <category term="projects" label="projects"/>
    <category term="development" label="development"/>
    <published>2014-11-12T00:00:00+00:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://jnrowe.github.io/articles/new_love_giddiness.html</id>
    <title>Giddy new project love</title>
    <updated>2018-12-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>James Rowe</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;section id="giddy-new-project-love"&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve recently inherited a new tier-one project, which is great news!  Sadly, it
is in real need of some Tender Loving Care™.  Was there ever an inherited
project that wasn’t?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The project is our semi-custom transpiler for &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ada_(programming_language)"&gt;Ada&lt;/a&gt; affectionately called
&lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;sandfly&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;.  I say semi-custom as it was spun out from a consortium effort to
“facilitate reliability and improve portability” of &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;Ada&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; projects, which is
a far loftier sounding goal than it need be.  In essence, it is the
codification of rules and guidelines we’ve adhered to since a partner meeting
in &lt;em&gt;1996&lt;/em&gt;, and that we find ourselves still following today&lt;a class="footnote-reference brackets" href="#id4" id="id1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wasn’t around back when the original group was formed, and it was disbanded
before I’d even heard of &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;Ada&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;.  This project is genuinely
multi-generational, which &lt;em&gt;feels&lt;/em&gt; nice.  All too often our work in software can
feel ephemeral; squeaked on a whiteboard in the morning, tapped in to
a computer in the afternoon and swept away by the janitors as night falls.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section id="hopes-and-dreams"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Hopes and dreams&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the project &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; have significant longevity I find myself pondering the
future.  &lt;em&gt;If&lt;/em&gt; I could change things for the next 20 years, what should I do to
make that experience better?  Should I do &lt;em&gt;nothing at all&lt;/em&gt; and just chug along
reducing the anxiety that even small changes will evoke?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also find myself pondering the present.  Could a truly radical change &lt;em&gt;today&lt;/em&gt;
obviate the need for this project entirely before the next maintainer grabs the
reins for their reign of anxiety?  Would that necessarily be a good thing?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;aside class="sidebar"&gt;
&lt;p class="sidebar-title"&gt;Common errors&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve always considered it odd that we can choose to attach a listing of
common errors to a product and expect people to use it.  If we know it is
common for users to make critical errors because of a design decision we
need to make a new design, not a new bullet point on the list.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even simple things like watching an &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;Ada&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; beginner make the classic
“atomic means atomic” mistake should be designed out, and not &lt;em&gt;solved&lt;/em&gt; with
an addendum of “protected objects mean atomic” chicanery.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many of the advantages that we associate with &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;Ada&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; — such as its mighty type
safety — no longer feel that advanced or remotely unique.  Even “hobby”
languages such as &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://nim-lang.org/"&gt;nim&lt;/a&gt; implement many of the safety features we expect from
&lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;Ada&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; implementations&lt;a class="footnote-reference brackets" href="#id5" id="id2"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;; subrange types being a fine example where the
&lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;nim&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; designers have absorbed an &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;Ada&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; feature.  And standard everyday
languages now often have tooling that is capable of providing &lt;em&gt;many&lt;/em&gt; of the
benefits of &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;Ada&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;, and one should really only expect this to increase.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What really hammers home the point here is that a good number of the features
one thinks about weren’t even available in &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;Ada&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; when &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;sandfly&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; began; fex
contracts are from &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.ada2012.org/"&gt;Ada 2012&lt;/a&gt;.  Will languages leapfrog &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;Ada&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; in its niche
by borrowing and then sprint away by innovating as their uptake increases?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="benefits-of-transpilation"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Benefits of transpilation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The original &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;sandfly&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; authors implemented a transpiler because it made
various checks simpler to carry out.  According to the documentation, it was
never intended to become a full blown language in its own right… which of
course it has.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe we should take the opportunity to stay on top of the changing language
landscape thanks to the side effect of &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;sandfly&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;’s implementation details.
Given that we’re already transpiling should we consider alternative targets?
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.ocaml.org/"&gt;ocaml&lt;/a&gt; is the language that immediately jumps to mind, as it is syntactically
close to &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;sandfly&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; and it has an excellent type system.  And once you have
&lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;ocaml&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; it is a smaller step to &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://fsharp.org/"&gt;F#&lt;/a&gt; thanks to its legacy &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;ocaml&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; mode.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The code base is amenable to multiple targets already.  A couple of years ago
I implemented support for testing without relying on the support kernel
supplied by our compiler vendor&lt;a class="footnote-reference brackets" href="#id6" id="id3"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;.  At its base &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;sandfly&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; will optionally
generate &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.lua.org/"&gt;lua&lt;/a&gt; bytecode that is loaded in to a tiny emulator which can be driven
by other &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;lua&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; scripts to test an implementation.  Its main purpose was to
allow early experimentation without the expense and time of waiting for
hardware re-fabrication.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class="align-default" id="id7"&gt;
&lt;img alt="sandfly debug architecture" src="../../_images/sandfly_use.png" style="width: 279.5px; height: 358.0px;" /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="caption-text"&gt;As you can see from example usage, it’s source-to-source all the way down.
If I’m writing &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;lua&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; I’m using &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/leafo/moonscript/"&gt;moonscript&lt;/a&gt;, and so should you!&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m not sure it would even be a great stretch to change the main target, there
would likely be significant support for it in fact.  It has already been
suggested that we should exclusively switch to &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/SPARK_(programming_language)"&gt;spark&lt;/a&gt; on a number of occasions,
especially since the reformation in Spark 2014.  If we could figure out the
safety certification story I’m sure there would be a lot of traction for &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;F#&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;
as default.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="final-thoughts"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Final thoughts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;aside class="sidebar"&gt;
&lt;p class="sidebar-title"&gt;Open Sourcing &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;sandfly&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There have been a few enquiries as to whether this work is Open Source, and
sadly it isn’t.  However, if you work for one of the Atlas Consortium
companies(or a significant partner of one) it is easy to arrange “source
available” access.  I &lt;em&gt;know&lt;/em&gt; this isn’t the same thing, but it is the
current situation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The good news is that I’ve added an item to the issue tracker that includes
making it Open Source, the bad news is that there is a lot of work needed
— both by me and &lt;em&gt;many&lt;/em&gt; others — to make that happen.  I’ve kicked the
initial process off by contacting legal for guidance, we’ll see what
happens.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve always really appreciated &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vala_(programming_language)"&gt;vala&lt;/a&gt;’s alternative syntax support; &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/C_Sharp_(programming_language)"&gt;C#&lt;/a&gt; by
default, but with first class support for &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Genie_(programming_language)"&gt;genie&lt;/a&gt;’s &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://boo-lang.org/"&gt;boo&lt;/a&gt;-inspired syntax.
I find myself thinking how nice it would be to emulate that and have multiple
frontends, &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; the previously described backends.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact I find myself thinking about &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;vala&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; a lot as I write this.  It never
had the uptake I would have hoped for when I first read about it.  It has
however had a &lt;em&gt;huge&lt;/em&gt; impact in the places where it has been used.  That surely
makes it a great role model for &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;sandfly&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; going forward.  It is better to be
an elusive Aston Martin &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aston_Martin_DB5"&gt;DB-5&lt;/a&gt; than a common as muck &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ford_Focus"&gt;Ford Focus&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, I’m deep in a pre-reality dream state where I want to add heaps of amazing
new features and functionality, coupled with a cold light of day feeling that
it could be nice to kill the project by transforming it in to a gateway out of
&lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;Ada&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;.  It could be the best &lt;em&gt;or&lt;/em&gt; worst project in the history of the world!
I’m genuinely excited.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="rubric"&gt;Footnotes&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;dl class="footnote brackets"&gt;
&lt;dt class="label" id="id4"&gt;&lt;span class="brackets"&gt;&lt;a class="fn-backref" href="#id1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;&lt;p&gt;It should be easy to guess why this project is being handed on, given
that we’re talking about a twenty-one year old endeavour.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt class="label" id="id5"&gt;&lt;span class="brackets"&gt;&lt;a class="fn-backref" href="#id2"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;&lt;p&gt;This isn’t meant to disparage &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://nim-lang.org/"&gt;nim&lt;/a&gt;, as it is really quite interesting.
I mean it purely in the sense that we haven’t &lt;em&gt;yet&lt;/em&gt; seen large industry
adoption.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt class="label" id="id6"&gt;&lt;span class="brackets"&gt;&lt;a class="fn-backref" href="#id3"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;&lt;p&gt;I’m of the &lt;em&gt;strong&lt;/em&gt; opinion that vendors who forbid you from naming,
shaming and even benchmarking them should be avoided at &lt;em&gt;all costs&lt;/em&gt;.
However, I’m not on the procurement board and didn’t get to make that
decision.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="https://jnrowe.github.io/articles/new_love_giddiness.html" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>I’ve recently inherited a new tier-one project, which is great news!  Sadly, it
is in real need of some Tender Loving Care™.  Was there ever an inherited
project that wasn’t?sandfly debug architecture</summary>
    <category term="tools" label="tools"/>
    <category term="projects" label="projects"/>
    <category term="languages" label="languages"/>
    <published>2018-12-04T00:00:00+00:00</published>
  </entry>
</feed>
